Hey again, everyone.
This is Dr. Ermin Tala
here with the second
session in our series on
clinical cardiology. So
last lecture, we focused
on the ECG complex, its
components, vectors,
Ithobin's triangle, throughout
the lens of cardiac physiology.
Now in this lecture,
we'll apply those concepts
to more clinical
applications, connecting
our understanding of
the EKG complex with the
mechanical contractions
in the heart muscle.
After that, we'll
review the blood flow
of coronary arteries
and how these
correspond to specific
lead locations.
Then, we'll jump into the
approach of reading an
EKG from start to finish.
In the end, I'll provide
two examples of EKG
presentations. So let's begin.
These are the session
objectives for this
lecture. The questions
selected on your upcoming
exams reflect these
objectives. So again,
if you can answer
these questions in your
own words, you probably
are in a good spot.
In the bottom right corner,
we also have corresponding
pages in the first aid
book for reference.
I decided to include this
quote here from D.H. Lawrence,
the eyes cannot see what
the mind does not know.
This was actually a
quote that was said to me
during my third year
clinical rotations by a
pulmonologist. And I think
this quote in particular
really correlates to the
ability to read an EKG.
Reading an EKG is a
developed skill, and the
eyes won't be able to
interpret or really
recognize anomalies in an
EKG until we learn about
what is a normal EKG
and what are these
anomalies that we should
look after or look for.
So I included Wigger's
diagram here. You'll
be exposed to this in
another lecture, so I
don't want to overwhelm
you all with this,
especially with all
the details of the
pressure differences
within the diagram.
What I want you to
take away from this
slide is connecting the
ECG complex components
with the correlating
mechanical events.
Exposing you to different
varieties of the same
material can help create
mental models that
encompasses all the details
of the cardiac cycle.
If you can explain
what's going on at each
point along this
graph, you have a
strong understanding
of cardiac physiology.
To be honest, the
point of including
Wigger's diagram here
is to connect us back
to the first lecture
on ECG complexes,
kind of hammering
home the mechanical
underworkings of the heart.
So on the top, you can
see an EKG complex.
You see the P-wave, QRS
complex, and T-wave.
In the first lecture,
we discussed what
each of these
inflections represent.
So understanding the
coronary blood flow is
pretty important when it
comes to identifying a
heart attack or myocardial
infarction, an MI.
So starting from the aorta,
the vessels that branch
off of it are the two
main arteries that supply
the heart with blood,
the right coronary artery
and the left main
coronary artery. Since the
heart is a muscle and
constantly pumping blood,
it's extremely dependent
on oxygen, and the only
organ to be supplied with
oxygen during diastole.
The right coronary
artery in a right
dominant heart, which
is also most common,
then becomes the posterior
descending artery,
the PDA. In a left
dominant heart, the PDA
may come off of the
left circumflex artery.
For the most part on
exams, you will assume that
the heart is right
dominant, as it usually is.
Right coronary artery,
RCA supplies the SA and AV
nodes, which can be very
important if occluded, in what
is known as the inferior
view of the heart through
the PDA. You can think that
this is inferior because
the heart is retroverted,
tilted back, and rotated
to the left, like we mentioned
in the prior lecture.
And again, this means
that the inferior
portion of the
heart, the back of
the heart, is
supplied by the PDA.
Now, the left main
coronary artery
branches into the
left circumflex artery
and the left anterior
descending artery.
The left circumflex wraps
around the left side
of the heart providing
what is known as the
lateral view because
this is the left lateral
portion of the left
atrium and ventricle.
Last to discuss is the
left anterior descending
artery which runs down the
anterior portion of the
heart. A way to remember
this is to remind yourself
that this is the artery
that's also called the
anterior interventricular
artery located anteriorly
between the ventricles, the
right and left ventricle.
For this reason, it
contains two major views
commonly joined together
clinically, the anterior view
due to the anatomical
location and the septal view
because it supplies the
interventricular septum.
So NMI is most commonly
caused by plaque buildup
that ruptures. So
atherosclerotic, usually an origin
that leads to thrombus
formation. The reason
anatomically is important
because the treatment for an
MI goes along with the
region that is being
obstructed and usually involves
going into the heart with
a long tiny tube called
a catheter to open up the
blockage. An extremely
helpful way to approach
medicine in general is
to break down challenging
scientific words, especially
in pathology, trust me.
angiography so if we
break that word down angio
refers to vessel and
agography refers to some sort
of writing or in this
case a graphic picture so
in this case angiography
is our way of viewing
the sizes of the coronary
vessels and during the
procedure the physician
will shoot dye into the
coronary arteries x-ray
allows us to visualize and
then allows us to view
the dyes in the vessels
Once we confirm that the
patient has a critical
percentage block in a
coronary artery, we can
then form a plan to
restore blood flow and
leave the obstruction to
that area of the heart.
So in the past two
slides, we reviewed the
anatomy of the coronary
vessels and connected
these to different
viewpoints of the heart.
So why do we care
about the anatomy?
Because the ECG
provides an electrical
representation of what's
going on anatomically.
So on a 12-lead ECG, there
are corresponding leads
that show us the same views
that the arteries show us.
The trick as a medical
student is to associate
the correlating leads
to view the arteries.
Over time, you'll think
of the mostly clinical
relevant information.
You'll see an ECG and
quickly identify where the
SC segments are elevated
and identify which
artery is being occluded.
So when we look at these
corresponding leads, we
can start first with the
right coronary artery.
So the right coronary
artery is correlated with
what is known as the
inferior view of the heart.
On the EKG, this corresponds
to the leads 2, 3, and AVF.
The left anterior
descending artery shows the
septal and anterior views
as we mentioned before.
So in an EKG, this can be
seen using V1, V2, V3, and V4.
the left circumflex
artery shows the
lateral view. So on
the EKG, we can deduce
this using the V5,
V6, and AVL leads.
These leads in this
slide in general is
super high yield, not
only for boards, but
also clinical rotations
and in medicine.
So here you can see the
schematic of the coronary
artery groups on a 12-lead
EKG. So we have 2, 3, and AVF
for the right coronary
artery, v1 to v4 for the left
anterior descending artery
and v5 v6 avl for the left
circumflex artery again
this is clinically important
for stemis because the
diagnosis that means you need
to see sc elevations in
two or more anatomically
contiguous leads so anatomically
contiguous means that the
leads fall within the same
cornea artery so v1 and
v2 are considered anatomically
contiguous because they
both belong to the left
anterior descending artery.
These 1 and 2 are not
anatomically contiguous
because 1 falls under
the left circumflex
while 2 falls under
the right coronary.
So a mnemonic to remember the
cardiac views
within EKG is Sally.
For this reason, I
included a picture of
Sally Fields from
Forrest Gump. It's a
pretty good movie, so if
you have a movie night
in between your
studying and lectures,
I highly recommend.
So just going through
it. So the S is going
to stand for a septal
view corresponding
with leads V1 and
V2. A for an anterior
view corresponding
with leads V3 and V4.
You can remember this
because they're on the
anterior wall of the
picordium after V1 and V2.
And L stands for the lateral
view and the corresponding
leads are V5, V6, 1, and
AVL. If you remember the
vectors for 1 and AVL, they
point towards the lateral
wall of the heart, supplying
by the left circumflex.
Lastly,
I stands for inferior
view, and the
corresponding leads
are 2, 3, and AVF.
So if you're a visual
learner, I included a link
to a great 3D model of
where the leads correspond
to on the heart. I would
definitely recommend
spending some time
looking over this, and it
kind of gives you a visual,
more in-depth representation
of what we've been
talking about in relation
to different views and
fields of the heart.
So now, try to think to
yourself, what usually
happens mechanically
during the ST segment?
Correct.
Mechanical contraction
of the ventricles.
So in an MI, the heart
muscle is usually
ischemic, so
abnormalities are going
to be present within
the SC segment.
Usually, the SC segment
is isoelectric, which
basically means that it's
a flat line between the end
of the P wave and the
onset of the QRS complex.
The TP segment, defined
as the flat line between
the end of the T wave and
the start of the P wave is
a good reference point
to use. It can be seen as
the gold standard or true
isoelectric line. And it's
a great way for us to assess
and look at when we're
deciding if there's any
SC elevation, because
there's not any electrical
activity happening during
the TP segment. During the
TP segment, the heart is
at electrical rest while
in diastole and is awaiting
the next electrical
signal to be sent from the
SA node to the atria to
contract. So the segment
will never fool you and
is the best part to use. I
particularly wanted to
highlight this point because
it can be confusing sometimes
when we're trying to
see if there's SC elevation
or not. So the TP segment
is usually a solid segment
we can use to deduce that.
And again, this isn't
a pathology lecture on
STEMIs, but something to
consider is the difference
between ST depression
and ST elevation. So this
is particularly important
because ST depression
denotes ischemia. While
they both denote ischemia,
ST depression
denotes ischemia only
affecting the
subendocardium of the heart.
ST elevation is more of an
emergency because it denotes
a transmural ischemia,
meaning that it's affecting
all layers of the heart the
myocardium epicardium and
the endocardium and just
on the side here i included
this mnemonic pales that
i like it's a great way to
commit to memory and what leads
you can see some reciprocal
changes on the ecg when you
have a stemmy by reciprocal
changes we mean if there's
st elevation in one
set of leads there will
be corresponding st set XC
segment, depression, and other.
This can be super helpful,
a good reference point, and
will be useful later on.
So looking at this
EKG, if we were
to orient ourselves
to what this is,
ask yourself the
question, is this a series
of rhythm strips or
is it a 12-lead EKG?
As you correctly stated,
it is a 12-lead EKG.
So now I'm going to
be nice to you and
tell you that this
patient is experiencing
an MI. So the question
is, which leads,
views, and arteries are
being affected here?
In terms of contiguous
leads, as we discussed prior,
we can see SC segment
elevation and leads V2 to V4.
This covers the
septal view of the
heart, which means
that the left anterior
descending artery
is likely occluded.
And just for reference,
the left anterior
descending artery
is most commonly
included and can be
particularly fatal.
So again, now with
this EKG, if we were to
orient ourselves, we
should ask ourselves,
is this a series of
rhythm shifts or is
this a 12-lead EKG? So
again, as previously,
this is a 12 lead EKG.
So when we look at this
EKG, what do we see?
We see some SC
segment elevations
in which particular leads.
Starting from the left,
lead one, I don't really see
any SC segment elevation.
Although I do see it in lead
two, I do see some
in lead three.
I also see some in V1.
I also see some in
ABF, some in V2.
So the definition that we
talked about before is that
in terms of anatomically
contiguous leads, we can see
that there's SC segment
elevations in 2, 3, and AVF.
This covers the inferior view
of the heart, which means
that the right coronary
artery is likely occluded.
We also do see some V1,
V2 SC segment elevation
like we mentioned, which
means that this can
actually be part of a
septal inferior infarct.
So this is a good learning
point to kind of stress
that not only one part of the
heart needs to be affected
when there is an MI. It
can be more global and
more serious than we are
initially thought to think.
So objective one
question. So I'll
give you guys about 10 seconds.
pause the video, and then
we can review the question.
All right,
so which of the following
is not a correct correlation
of cardiac view with leads?
LAD, V1 to V4,
right coronary artery, 2,
3 AVF, or left circumflex
artery, V5, V6, 1 AVL,
or none of the above.
So the answer, as you
correctly stated, would be
none of the above. So these
are all correct correlations
of cardiac view with
leads, right? We mentioned
left anterior descending
artery is to the anterior
view of the heart involving
B1, B2, and B3, B4.
LED can be grouped,
like we said, into
anterior septal view
comprising all of
those leads. Right
circle flex artery,
right coronary artery,
2,3 AVF, inferior
view and left
circumflex V5V6, 1 AVL.
Next question again,
take about 10 seconds.
We'll pause the video
and we'll go over it.
So a patient presents
with classical
signs and symptoms of an MI.
On an EKG, you find
SC segment elevation
in leads 1 and 2,
what do you diagnose?
Anterior STEMI, inferior STEMI,
septal STEMI, or need more
information to diagnose?
So as you correctly
stated, we would
need more information
to diagnose.
Now the reason why this
is, as we spoke before,
to diagnose an MI in a
specific region of the heart,
we would need SC segment
changes, or in this
case elevations, and two
or more contiguous leads.
So now we'll be jumping
into the methodology
of reading in EKG using
a variation of Dr.
Cohen's EKG method that
he teaches during lunch
and learn sessions on
Mondays. So first, we
will orient ourselves
to what we're reading.
If we know we're
reading a rhythm strip
instead of a 12-lead EKG,
we're limited in what
we can take from the
cardiac monitoring.
After that, we can
calculate the rate,
rhythm, and axis. You should
have a good understanding
of axis from last lecture
down and to the left.
Lastly, we look at intervals
and others because it's
easier than saying sc
segment t-wave and other
abnormalities now a good
mnemonic to remember this method
of orient rate rhythm axis
and intervals and others
is officer ryan reynolds
always impresses others
after winning sexiest
man alive in 2010 ryan
reynolds played a very
handsome police officer in
irpd in 2013 if this
picture doesn't help you
remember how to read an
akg i'm not sure what will
So the more you practice
this, the better you will
get an EKG reading. And the
more Ryan Reynolds movies
you watch, the more you'll
remember the picture.
So hopefully, you can
remember the position
you're in now once
you get to your
rotations and practice,
practice, practice.
Now, while on your
rotations, you'll see
that most ECG machines
have a software that
reads the ECG and
can provide findings
at the top of the
rhythm strip or 12-lead.
So it's a good
practice to cover this
up so that you can
practice your skills.
So now, let's begin
with step one,
orient,
aka officer in our mnemonic.
So orient, or
orientation, refers
to what do we have
in front of us?
Are we looking at a 12 lead, a
rhythm strip, or a
few rhythm strips?
We reviewed how to
identify a 12 lead
versus a rhythm strip
in our last lecture.
Second part of
orientation is to look and
make sure that our monitoring
system is calibrated
correctly. It's not
something that you'll
necessarily need to
know for boards or BS
during upcoming exams,
but I figured it'd be good
for you to be exposed to
it. So when you look at
the beginning or the end
of a 12 lead, you'll notice
a calibration box of two
big boxes or 10 little
boxes high and one big
box or five little boxes
across. This shows the normal
calibration of the ECG.
We just mentioned on the
previous slide how the
ECG paper is organized
into little and big boxes.
Once normally calibrated,
we know that these boxes
correspond to specific times
that can help us identify
both the rate and any
prolongations and intervals.
Each small box where
represents 0.4 seconds.
You can see one small
box here, and if you
were to multiply the
number of small boxes in
a big box, which are
these five little boxes,
your incredibly smart
minds will calculate
that one large box
yields 0.2 seconds.
This becomes important
when measuring, like we
mentioned, any interval,
prolongations, and ECG
parameters. And also
as a tip, the speed of
the ECG is around 25
millimeters per second with
a calibration of 10
millimeters per millivolt.
So now step two, rate,
or from our harmonic,
Ryan. So calculating rate
is an important part of
describing a patient's
condition. The rate is
the amount of beats per
minute, beats per minute.
So by rate, we're
referring to heart rate.
So tachycardia is a
heart rate that's greater
than 100 beats per minute,
while bradycardia is
one defined as less than
60 beats per minute.
So rate, besides for showing
up on a monitor associated
with the pulse ox, can be
calculated in different
ways, depending on your
method of looking at an ECG.
I'll introduce you to
three methods. We should
stick to the one that
works best for you,
or the one for the
right clinical scenario.
So, the first
method banks on the
idea that you remember
that a standard
printed rhythm
strip is 10 seconds.
If you count the number of
QRS complexes across the
rhythm strip, you should
get the number of beats per
second. If you multiply this
by 6, you get the total number
of beats in 60 seconds, in
other words, how many beats
per minute. This method
is best when you have an
abnormal rhythm, such as
atrial fibrillation or flutter.
The second method utilizes
the distance between each
QRS complex, specifically
the R wave or the R
upstroke. This is my preferred
method of finding the
rate, so you'll start at a
QRS that lies directly on
top of a thick vertical
line, and then if you were to
count the number of big
boxes away to the next QRS
complex, the peak of the R
wave, there's a predictable
beats per minute associated
with each box you
jump over. If you jump over
one big box and you find
a QRS, your rate is 300
beats per minute. If you go
two big boxes over, your
rate is 150 beats per minute.
This continues and follows
a pattern 300, 150,
100, 75, 65, 50 beats per
minute for each large box.
And as an example, if
your QRS complex is
between 4 and 5 big
boxes away from your
first QRS complex,
how many beats per
minute is your rate?
What would you think?
As you correctly stated,
it would be somewhere
between 75 and 60 beats
per minute, which is the
normal rate for the
average person. This method
is particularly suitable
for regular rhythms.
So method three also utilizes
distances between
two QRS complexes.
Here you find the number
of big boxes between
two QRS complexes and
divide 300 by that number.
This was or is not really
the preferred option I've
seen amongst medical
students. It wasn't mine
in the beginning, but it's
something that I've grown
accustomed to and a
method that I like. So if
this is particularly one
that you think would be a
good option for you it
involves less memorization
try it out it may be beneficial
and maybe your preferred option
so just continuing along
this is here's an example
finding rate something you
can come back to on your
own time to see which method
you like best now if a
patient has normal sinus
rhythm then you can use any
of these methods that
we've described because you
have the same distance between
the QRS complexes. If a
patient doesn't have a
normal sinus rhythm, like we
mentioned before in the
case of itrofibrillation,
if you were to use method
two, you'll receive different
rates based on which QRS
you choose, as these are
not equally spaced. To
say that again, to really
hammer it home, when the rhythm
is irregular, it's better
to count how many complexes
on the whole strip
and multiply by six. Because
if you're counting between
only two QRS complexes,
because you can get very
different numbers depending
on which two you choose.
So many students have
difficulty understanding
the difference between
rate and rhythm.
Rate is simply the
heart rate in beats per
minute, like we mentioned.
So bradycardic, less
than 60 beats per minute,
tachycardic, greater
than 100, or normal
rate between 60 to 100.
You can have a normal
rate with an abnormal
rhythm. You can also
have an abnormal rate
with a normal rhythm.
So I highly recommend
separating rate and
rhythm every time you come
to a new EKG, so you
don't confuse yourself.
So step number three,
rhythm, or in our mnemonic,
Reynolds.
So normal sinus
rhythm is defined as
a P wave preceding
all QRS complexes.
You can see this in the
top left-hand corner,
where we have all of our
P waves. So, P wave here,
P wave here, P wave here,
P wave here, and etc.
So, on clinical rotations,
many physicians,
especially in the ER, will
try to identify atrial
fibrillation, as
this is the most common
cause of strokes.
So, atrial fibrillation is
seen in the top right-hand
corner, in which there is
no true P waves. So if we
were to compare this rhythm
strip to our previous one
here, here we see well-defined
P-waves as we mentioned
before, but there are not
really any good P-waves
here. What we see here are
known as virulatory waves,
aka not true P
-waves. And as we can
tell here, the
distances between one
QRS complex to
another are varying,
a.k.a.
they're irregular,
meaning this is
an irregularly
irregular rhythm.
Again, in AFib, before
we go into it deeper in
future lectures, there's
no distinct P waves,
simply just random
squiggling back and forth.
So in the bottom left,
you'll see something that's
really tricky, almost like
normal sinus rhythm. So if
you look closely, there are
P waves with no linked QRS
complex immediately after
it. These P waves are not
necessarily associated with
the QRS complex, but the
rate is regular, as is the
P wave. This is because
this represents when the atria
in particular beat without
synchronization in what
is known as complete or
third degree AV or heart
block, another abnormal rhythm
that we'll get on and focus
on in a future lecture.
And lastly, in the
bottom right-hand corner,
you'll see a flat
line called asystole.
If you see this and your
patient is looking fine,
it's probably because
something's unplugged.
But if you see this and
your patient's unresponsive,
that's because they're
in cardiac arrest,
aka dead, and need
immediate resuscitation.
All in all, I wouldn't again
focus too much about the
specifics of what we
mentioned, atrial fibrillation,
AV blocks, etc., as we'll
discuss this in a later
lecture. What's very
important now is that you can
identify normal sinus rhythm,
that every P wave precedes
a QRS complex and every
P wave has a QRS complex.
So after you determine if
the rhythm is or is not
sinus rhythm, it's time to
determine if your rhythm
is regular or irregular.
So many students combine
these two steps with more
practice. On the left,
you can see a regular
rhythm. If you took a line
piece of paper or calipers
and noted all the R
waves, they would be
equidistant from each other.
On the right is an
irregular rhythm. You can
see immediately the R
waves are not equidistant
from one another.
For harder cases,
using the paper method
or calipers would help
you define or identify
an irregular rhythm.
So next, step number
four, determine
the axis, or always
in our mnemonic.
So sorry to trigger
you guys again, but
we're back to axis from
our previous lecture.
So remember that the axis
is the major direction
of electrical activity
flowing through the heart.
If the heart is hypertrophied
in any location, this may
cause the signal to travel
farther and change the
direction of the vector. The
most efficient way to estimate
or look at the axis is
comparing the direction or
orientation of the QRS
complexes in lead 1 and AVF. As
you mentioned prior, if
we go back to Eindhoven's
triangle, we saw that leads 1
and AVF were perpendicular to
each other, meaning those
are the best two leads to
use to compare. This is also
the preferred method that
Dr. Cohen likes to use and
a method that I continue to
use. So now continuing along
with the open triangle as
we mentioned in the prior
slide in previous lecture.
Positive inflection means
that we have depolarization
that occurs towards
a lead. Now as you
mentioned just before the
two leads that we use are
right leads one in AVF
one determining the axis.
So we spoke in great
detail about vectors, but
here we're going to use
an easier method that
will help you on your
clinical rotations to quickly
identify if your axis
is normal or abnormal.
The method that we want to
use is called the thumbs
up method. So if your
left hand represents
lead one and your right
hand represents lead AVF,
you can determine the
axis. You can even pull out
your thumbs right now,
practice alone in your
cubicle with a loved one
or a random person on the
street. If you really
want to hammer this home.
So thumbs up refers to
a positive QRS complex.
Thumbs down refers to a
negative QRS complex. If your
ECG comes to you, you've
already oriented yourself,
have your rate rhythm,
you could drop the EKG and
put your thumbs out. So if
both of your thumbs go up,
this means that there's a
positive inflection of the
QRS complex and leads one
in AVF, meaning you have a
normal axis. If both hands
are down, meaning you have
a negative inflection of
the QRS complex in leads 1
and AVF, this means you
have an extreme axis. This
doesn't happen too often, to
be honest. You'll most likely
encounter left or rightward
axis deviations, meaning
in a leftward axis deviation,
you have your thumb
pointing upward, your left
hand in lead 1, and your
thumb on your right hand
pointing downward in lead AVF
and the opposite occurring
for right axis deviation.
Your left thumb pointing
downward for lead 1 and
your right thumb pointing
upward for lead AVF.
So there are a bunch of
causes of axis deviation.
Some of the high yield
ones are listed here.
For board's sake though,
I would definitely
know left ventricular
hypertrophy causes left
axis deviation and
how to identify it. it
was one that actually
came up on my comlex.
So I won't include questions
here because of the
ending where we'll be
reviewing two ECGs together.
This encompasses both
objective two and three.
So now step five, we're
on intervals or impresses
in our mnemonic. So
the PR interval normal
duration is between 120
to 200 milliseconds.
Longer than one big box would
therefore be a prolonged
PR interval. Remember,
this is the time it takes
to get from the SA through
the AV node. So for this
reason, PR interval is crucial
in identifying AV blocks.
It's an important measure
that you should definitely
know for clinical practice
and for board exams.
So the normal QRS
duration is less
than 120 milliseconds,
or three boxes.
The way I like to
remember this is there are
three letters in QRS, so
I know that the normal
duration of a QRS complex
is three small boxes.
Now, a widened QRS
complex has many causes,
as we discussed in
the previous lectures,
such as bundle branch
block, hyperkalemia,
tricyclic or TCAs, Wolf
-Parkinson-White syndrome,
ventricular pacing, and
hypothermia. They're all tied to
physiology, so feel free to
go back and review any of
these pathologies or email
me to discuss them further.
Now, a prolonged QT interval
is very important to be
able to identify because
a prolonged QT interval
increases the risk of dangerous
arrhythmias, particularly
ventricular arrhythmias
like torsionis de point,
which can then degenerate
into lethal arrhythmias
such as ventricular
fibrillation. Now, a good
rule of thumb is that a
normal QT is less than half
of the R to R ratio. So
if we were to go between
two R waves, so we have
our, excuse me, our P wave,
Q, R, S, all by our T wave,
and then again, our P wave,
Q, R, S, T wave.
Now the distance
between these two
we'd want our QT interval,
which starts from the
beginning of our Q wave
to the end of the T wave
to occur before we
meet the halfway
point between these R waves,
which is relatively
along this line.
I apologize, I am
not the best artist.
In other terms, the
normal QT interval
is between 0.36
to 0.44 seconds.
This can slightly change
between genders, but
is a good reference
point in numbers to know.
A mnemonic to remember
as well as some causes
of a prolonged QT
interval is the mnemonic
as we mentioned in
the previous lecture,
ABCDEF.
We also have congenital
causes of QT prolongation,
such as long QT
syndrome and electrolyte
abnormalities that we
will discuss later on.
So our last step,
step number six,
others, also others
in our mnemonic.
So during assessment of
other things in EKG, we can
look at things like our
SC segment and T waves.
We'll leave it limited to
this at the basic level.
So both changes in either
SC segments or T waves
can indicate some form of
ischemia of heart muscle.
Like we mentioned earlier
in the lecture, we know
that SC depression means
that ischemia is limited
to the sub and the cardio
layer, while SC elevation
is transmural, involving
all layers of the heart.
So in an EKG, we can
see SC segment changes.
Now, like we mentioned before,
although SC segment should
always be isoelectric,
it sometimes will not be,
as is the case in an MI, be
it SC segment elevation
or SC segment depression.
This is why I wanted to
mention earlier on that
the TP segment can be a
great reference point to
use. So just keep that
in the back of your mind.
So for Bohr's purposes,
the T-wave represents
ventricular repolarization,
as we mentioned earlier.
A peak T-wave is a
sign of hyperkalemia,
and a flattened T-wave with a
prominent U-wave is a
sign of hypokalemia.
This makes sense
because if you remember,
potassium is part of
the repolarization
stage, phase 3 of
the action potential.
So if you're affecting
repolarization, this
would be reflected by
changes in the QT interval,
T-wave, and if severe
enough, the QRS complex.
So in the clinical setting,
inverted T-waves is one
of the first signs of cardiac
ischemia, making T-waves
an important indicator of
whether or not a person
is experiencing some form
of acute coronary syndrome.
So now, let's try to
interpret this EKG in front of
us using the steps that
we've learned along the way.
So just to reiterate, we
have our orientation, then
rate, rhythm, axis,
intervals, and then others.
So beginning with
step number one,
orientation, we want
to orient ourselves.
Ask ourselves, what
are we looking at?
Are we looking at a
12-lead EKG, rhythm
strips, and what
is the calibration
curve? Is it appropriate?
Is it normal?
So looking at this EKG
in front of us, we can
count 12 leads, right?
So we have 1, 2, 3, AVR,
AVL, AVF, V1 to V6, for
a total of 12 leads.
Now to assess the
calibration curve we
see that the calibration
curve in this
EKG is on the left
side of the screen.
So a normal calibration
curve is two big boxes
in height and one big
box in width, which is
the calibration curve
that we see here. So now
we know that we're looking
at a 12 lead EKG with
an appropriate, or
normal calibration curve.
Next, we can assess the rate.
So to assess the rate,
we can find any of
our leads. Let's just
look at lead one,
find our QRS complexes.
And in this case, we
can take and assess the
distance between one QRS
complex to the other.
So between these two QRS
complexes, we have about
five big boxes. And
again, between this QRS
complex to the other, we
have about five big boxes.
Now, using one of the
methods we learned
earlier, if we were to
use the number of big
boxes between two
consecutive QRS complexes,
we can do 300 divided by
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, which gives
us a heart rate of approximately
60 beats per minute.
So our rate is approximately
Now the rhythm.
Next step.
So to assess the rhythm,
first we want to locate
or identify if we have any
P waves. Now the P waves,
which should precede
each QRS complex, can be
found in any of the leads,
but particularly there are
some leads that are, as
Dr. Collins referred to
them, the money leads. Now
the money leads are the
leads that will show us
the most prominent or the
best P waves. So when in
doubt, these are the leads
you want to look at if
you can't really discern
from other leads if there
are any P waves present.
These leads happen to be
leads 2, 3, AVF, and V1.
So in this case, lead
2, we see pretty good P
waves here with a good
morphology. So we see
a P wave in front of
each QRS complex here,
which tells us that the
rhythm is sinus rhythm.
Now, we can also
look at the distances
between the QRS
complexes. The QRS
complexes, as we
mentioned before,
using the method that we used
to assess the heart rate,
the QRS complexes' distances
between each other is
equal. So there's no
irregularities between the two.
Now, so we have our
orientation, we've oriented
ourselves, our rate, 60 beats
per minute approximately,
our rhythm, which
is sinus rhythm. And
now our next step
is going to be axis.
So when interpreting
axis, like we mentioned
earlier, we want to look
at leads one and AVF.
So lead one and AVF. We can
use our thumb rule as well.
So if you look at the
orientation of the R wave here,
the QRS complex, we see
that it's pointed upright.
So our thumb, our
left thumb is pointing
upright. And then looking
at ABF, we see the
same thing. Our QRS
complex is pointed upright,
so our right thumb
is pointed upright.
So two thumbs up, we're
thinking normal axis
with no deviation. All
right, simple enough.
next in our list is intervals
so now we can assess
intervals starting with our
pr interval as we mentioned
before anything that revolves
or involves the p wave
2 3 avf and v1 could be
really nice leads to look at
because the p waves have
the most distinct morphology
so in this case So if we
look at lead two, we can see
our P wave here, and we
can assess our PR interval.
So if we start from the
beginning of the P wave
to the beginning of
the R wave, we count
approximately about 1.4 big
boxes. This is an instance
where calipers would
be particularly useful.
This is approximately
about 0.38 seconds.
So this is particularly
prolonged, right?
Because as you mentioned
before, a normal PR
interval is about 0.12
to 0.2 seconds. So we
have a prolonged PR
interval in this case.
Next up, we can assess the
QRS complex, make sure it's
duration, and assess that.
So in this case, it's
about 1 to 1.5 big boxes, so
about 0.08 to 0.1 seconds.
Normal, it's really
hard to tell in
this case. but when
you see a really
tight QRS complex,
it's usually normal.
Next up, our QT interval.
So our QT interval,
again, we can start
from the beginning of
the Q wave here to
the end of the T wave.
We can assess this interval.
As we mentioned earlier,
our normal QT interval
is about 0.36 to 0.44
seconds. But when we're
on the wards, sometimes
we don't have time.
We're looking at a
bunch of EKGs. We
can't sit there
and count each one.
So as we mentioned before, we
can do kind of
the shortcut way.
We can find two consecutive
R waves and calculate
and draw an equidistant
line between the two.
So let's do that now.
So we're drawing our
equidistant line between
the two consecutive R waves.
And we see here,
again, not the best
artist. Maybe I can
draw a better line,
but our QT interval
finishes before we get to
that equidistant line,
meaning our T wave ends
before the line that we
drew, which to us for our
purposes means that the
QT interval is less than
half the R to R interval
and normal, all right?
Simple enough.
so next on our list after
intervals is assessing
other things for our case
and purposes we're going
to look at sc segments
and t waves in the ckg
there are really not any
sc segment abnormalities
so normal sc segments so
we don't see any visible
depressions or sc segment
elevation looking at
t waves now we also see
normal t wave morphology
we don't see any peak T
waves or T wave inversions so
now that we've gone through
the steps of reading the
EKG we can now circle back
and talk about rhythm for
a second now the PR interval
that we mentioned was a
bit prolonged and we haven't
gotten over this yet but
as we mentioned before we
said the rhythm was sinus
rhythm but having a prolonged
PR interval that is fixed
is characteristic of an
arrhythmia known as first
degree AV block so we will
touch on this later but
our rhythm here is going
to be sinus rhythm with a
first degree AV block or
if we shorten that just
first degree av block so
if we were to take the tkg
and show it to our attending
we would say that we're
looking at a 1280 kg with
appropriate calibration
with a rate of 60 a rhythm
of first degree av block
or you can say sinus
rhythm with first degree av
block normal axis prolonged
pr interval of approximately
0.38 seconds, otherwise
normal and otherwise
all other intervals normal
with no ST or T changes.
So now having gone
through the first example,
we can go through this
example as well, probably
at a little bit of a
quicker pace now that we're
more acclimated and
experts at reading EKGs.
So first what we want
to do again is orient
ourselves. So in front of
us right now we have a 12
lead EKG because we can
count all 12 leads on
this ECG paper. The
calibration curve on the
left is also appropriately
calibrated because again
we have one big box in
width and two big boxes
in height giving us
appropriate calibration.
Now to calculate the rate again
we can look at the distance
between the QRS complexes,
count the number of big
boxes, and divide that by
300, or we can also count
the number of QRS complexes
and multiply by 6.
So in our case 10
QRS complexes can be
counted on the bottom
here and multiplied
by 6 gives us
about a rate of 60,
approximately.
So we've oriented
ourselves, we have a rate,
now what is our rhythm?
Now again, assessing
rhythm, we want to
look at our P waves and
make sure that we have
P waves with normal
morphology and preceding
each QRS complex.
And also that each
QRS complex is equally
spaced with no
irregularities in between.
So in our case, we
have P waves, although
with very, I would
say, low amplitude.
We do see some in lead one.
We see some in lead three.
And in V1 as well.
So we do have P
waves in front of
each QRS complex.
So normal sinus rhythm.
And then when we
go into axis, we can
see when we compare,
we have lead 1 and
then lead AVF, lead 1.
Our QRS complex is a bit what
would be called biphasic,
meaning that the QRS
complex itself is not 100%
pointing upward or downward.
It's about, I would say,
50% upward, 50% downward.
But judging from
the QRS complex here,
I would say it's
leaning more so positively
versus negatively.
And then we can compare
that as well to AVF, which
is QRS complex is upright.
So we have a normal cardiac
axis with no deviation
at this point. Looking at
intervals now, we have our
PR interval, which we can
assess, again, going from
the beginning of the P
wave to the onset of the
QRS complex, or the R wave.
And this gives us
approximately about
0.12 to 0.16 seconds,
which is normal.
QRS complex looks
very narrow, about one
box, two boxes, about
0.1 seconds, so normal.
QT interval, again,
we can assess that as
well, going from the
peak of the R wave,
between two consecutive
QRS complexes, and
then drawing a line
down the middle here.
and we see that our
T wave ends before
the onset of our
equidistant line.
So our QT interval
is normal, is less
than one half the
R to R interval.
So we've gone
through orientation,
rate, rhythm, axis, intervals.
The point of this EKG
really was to clue you into
all of the others. So in
this case, what are some
of the others that we
have here? Well, we have
pretty well-defined T
waves, if you can tell here,
right?
So they're pretty peaked,
and also we have some SC
segment elevation here as
well. So we have SC cell
segment elevation and leads
2, 3, AVF, which would
clue us into ischemia in
the inferior leads, right?
Leads 2, 3, AVF, which
is characteristic of an
inferior STEMI, right?
Because we have SC segment
elevation in these leads
as well as peaked T waves.
Now, if we were to
have an inferior STEMI,
right, where would
we think that we
would see reciprocal
changes? changes.
Using our mnemonic from before,
PALES, if we have SC segment
elevation in the inferior
leads, we would see reciprocal
changes in the lateral
leads, which would mean SC
segment depression, or T
wave inversion. Now our
lateral leads were leads one,
AVL,
V5, and V6. Now we do see
some reciprocal changes
in the leads one, AVL, so
two contiguous leads that
give us a view of the
lateral side of the heart,
which also can kind of
reconfirm to ourselves that
we're looking at what looks
like an inferior STEMI.
I hope that wasn't too
confusing, but it is very
useful to try and tie
all of these points in
together, especially the
more you read EKGs. And
when there are cases where
you're not 100% sure of
what's going on, you can
always use these rules
and relationships as
double checks for yourself.
Here's a summary slide that you
can look at on your own time.
And again, here we have
some of the objectives
here, as well as some
key points to review,
to know, to help both
on your exams, as well
as in digesting and
learning the information.
So that concludes
the second lecture.
I hope you find it valuable
to your learning and I
appreciate any feedback.
and feel free to email
me or the rest of the team
um team cohen also feel
free to join us on mondays
from 12 to 1 p.m eastern
standard time over zoom
with dr cohen to review
ecgs and to have more exposure
again the more exposure
the better ekg skills
and as always make sure
to take time some time for
yourself at least every
day because your mental
health is an important
aspect of developing yourself
as a person and physician.
So best of luck. See
you in the next lecture.